Guide to the Julius Hemphill Papers MSS.542
Fales Library and Special Collections
- Ebony, 1986-1995; cuid20456 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  Holograph score in pencil, with annotations in composer's hand in red ink, for big-band (five saxophones, five trumpets, four trombones, guitar, keyboard, bass, and drums). Arrangement of a composition by Jack DeJohnette. Folder includes second score in holograph for two background sections.
- Exotica, 1968-1995; cuid20457 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  Photocopy of page from Foran Notebook, not in composer's hand. Part for cello with instructions for improvisation. (May not be Hemphill composition.)
- Fanfare No. 5, 1968-1995; cuid20458 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  Photocopy of holograph score from Schirmer's Notebook for alto saxophone, tenor saxophone, and bass. From a sequence of pieces in Schirmer's Notebook for similar instrumentation.
- Fat Man, 1991-1995; cuid20459 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  Holograph score in pencil and blue ink for saxophone sextet (soprano, two altos, two tenors, and baritone). Score bears the titles "Cornered" and "Fat Man." The first page of the score has been cut in half. Folder includes holograph parts with annotations by members of the sextet, including instructions for improvisation on Hemphill's first alto part, as well as photocopies of professionally copied parts.
- Fat Web, 1968-1995; cuid20460 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  Photocopy of holograph score from Schirmer's Notebook for alto saxophone, tenor saxophone, and bass.
- Fifteen, 1991-1995; cuid20461 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  Holograph score for saxophone, cello, and drums. The page also bears the title "One Groove," and the second page of the score features the composition "Sixteen."
- First Event, 1978-1995; cuid20462 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  Holograph score for saxophone, guitar, bass, and drums. Professionally copied parts for alto saxophone, bass, and drums, with note in composer's hand indicating some parts to be performed ad lib.
- Five Chord Stud, 1993-1995; cuid20463 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  Holograph score for saxophone sextet, three alto, two tenor, and baritone sax. Holograph parts. Some parts bear alternative title, "Shorty."
- Fixation, 1981-1995; cuid20464 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  Professionally copied parts for saxophone quartet (soprano, two tenor, and baritone). Composition is part of a suite entitled "Wind/Rhythms" written for World Saxophone Quartet's collaboration with Max Roach's M'Boom. Percussion sections indicated in parts. See "Wind/Rhythms" for full score.
- Fixed Signs, 1976-1986; cuid20465 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  Professionally copied parts for saxophone quartet (two soprano saxophones, alto clarinet, and bass clarinet). Parts reflect specific instrumentation used by the World Saxophone Quartet.
- Flair, 1981-1995; cuid20466 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  Professionally copied parts for two flutes, alto flute, and bass clarinet. Each part has the number "11" at top of page, indicating order in a series of works. Composition is part of a suite entitled "Wind/Rhythms" written for World Saxophone Quartet's collaboration with Max Roach's M'Boom. See "Wind/Rhythms" for full score.
- Flat-Out Jump Suite, 1980-1995; cuid20467 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  Photocopy of holograph short score; holograph parts for trumpet, tenor saxophone, and cello. There is also an alto-saxophone transposition of the trumpet part in Marty Ehrlich's hand. This piece is included on the album Flat Out Jump Suite (1980) under the title "Body."
- Float, 1988-1995; cuid20468 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  Photocopy of holograph score from Musik Hug Notebook, as well as holograph parts for trumpet, guitar, and bass, which differ from the score. Score fragment with indication "After the original Float," indicating later extension of the work. This piece was arranged and titled "Floating" for the "Drunk on God" suite.
- Floppy / Blued Up, 1991-1995; cuid20469 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  Holograph score in pencil for saxophone sextet (three alto, two tenor, and baritone). Includes three sets of parts: photocopies of holograph parts except first alto saxophone part (see Aggregated Parts for originals), manuscript parts not in composer's hand, and photocopies of professionally copied parts used for the published sextet collection.
- Flush, 1990-1995; cuid20470 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  Holograph score for saxophone sextet (soprano, two alto, two tenor, and baritone). Includes manuscript parts likely in the hand of a sextet member, and photocopies of professionally copied parts used for the published sextet collection.
- Fly Dance, 1968-1995; cuid20471 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  Fragmentary holograph score in pencil. Of the four staves, one contains a 24-measure melody for flute. "Tenor" is written at the top of the page.
- For Billie - Scores, 1980-1995; cuid20472 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  Four holograph scores representing different arrangements and stages of composition. One-page holograph score with melody for alto saxophone in pencil and chords in red ink. Thirteen-page concert score for big band (five saxophones with flute doubling, trumpet, flugelhorn, trombone and baritone horn, and rhythm section). There is also a four-page extension of this big-band arrangement, with flute parts and annotations in pencil and red ink. Two-page score (transposed) for alto saxophone, trumpet, tenor saxophone, French horn, guitar, bass, and percussion.
- For Billie - Parts, 1980-1995; cuid20473 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  Complete set of professionally copied parts for big band (1980 version) on paper vellum. Additional professionally copied parts for two trumpets, trombone, and two guitars. There are also two guitar parts, one in holograph, one professionally copied, as well as an alto saxophone part with additional chordal writing.
- Four, 1968-1995; cuid20474 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  Photocopy of holograph score from Foran Notebook, for alto saxophone, trumpet, bass, and drums. See "One Two Three Four" for the other movements from this four-part suite. Folder includes various parts for alto saxophone, trumpet, guitar, cello, and bass, some in holograph, several of these photocopied from parts containing multiple pieces (see "Aggregated Parts").
- Functions, 1990-1995; cuid20475 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  Holograph score for saxophone quartet (alto, two tenor, and baritone) in blue and black ink. Four parts in manuscript, likely in Marty Ehrlich's hand, with additional annotations in various hands. One part includes chord notations in Hemphill's hand.
- Funny Paper, 1981-1995; cuid20476 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  Holograph parts in black ink for saxophone quartet (two altos, tenor, and baritone).
- G Song, 1977-1995; cuid20477 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  Photocopy of holograph short score from Musik Hug Notebook. The version of the piece on the album Raw Materials and Residuals (1977) differs in structure from this score. Holograph part for tenor saxophone, which resembles material in "A Bitter Glory" Notebooks.
- Georgia Blue, 1984-1995; cuid20478 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  Holograph score for saxophone quartet (solo alto, alto, tenor, and baritone saxophone). Holograph parts for quartet version for alto, tenor, and baritone saxophone. This piece was arranged for saxophone sextet (solo alto, soprano, alto, two tenor, and baritone) for the large-scale work "Long Tongues: A Saxophone Opera." Folder contains professionally copied parts for the sextet version. See "Long Tongues: A Saxophone Opera" for additional score and parts.
- Glide, 1991-1995; cuid20479 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  Holograph score (transposing) for saxophone sextet (three alto, two tenor, and baritone). Folder includes manuscript parts likely in the hand of a sextet member, and photocopies of professionally copied parts.
- Hand-Packed, 1980-1995; cuid20480 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  Holograph score for trumpet, tenor saxophone, cello, and percussion, including notes for copyist. Photocopies of professionally copied parts (originals in "Aggregated Parts").
- Hard Blues, The - Score and small group parts, 1972-1995; cuid20481 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  Photocopy of holograph score for alto saxophone, trumpet, and cello/bass from Chiaroscuro Notebook. Holograph part for cello (with instructions for drums), as well as professionally copied parts for trumpet and alto saxophone. Folder includes photocopy of holograph score for big-band arrangement (two soprano, alto, tenor, and baritone saxophones, two trumpets, trombone, tuba, vibraphone, bass, and drums), which premiered in 1980. Also includes one-page original holograph score with additional background parts. Folder includes parts for saxophone sextet arrangement, based on big-band parts. See also "Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land."
- Hard Blues, The - Big band parts, 1972-1995; cuid20482 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  Complete set of professionally copied parts in paper vellum and paper, as well as photocopies, for big-band arrangement.
- Harmonie, 1968-1995; cuid20483 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  Two photocopies of holograph part for cello, one with annotations in blue ink, the other with different annotations in black felt pen.
- Hazel's Light, 1968-1995; cuid20484 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  Holograph score (two pages) and professionally copied parts for flute, flugelhorn, marimba, and cello. Parts include annotations in composer's hand in red ink. Score includes instructions for percussionist. Marimba part includes note "with Joanne," possibly referring to dancer Joanne Robinson-Hill.
- Headlines, 1991-1995; cuid20485 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  Holograph transposing score for saxophone sextet (soprano, two alto, two tenor, and baritone). One original part in holograph for alto I, and photocopies of remaining holograph parts. Folder includes professionally copied parts for the published sextet collection.
- Hearts, 1977-1995; cuid20486 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  Photocopy of holograph score from Foran Notebook for saxophone quartet (two alto, tenor, and baritone). Folder includes photocopies of holograph parts.
- Holy Rockers, 1990-1995; cuid20487 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  Three related scores, composed for saxophone sextet and intended, though apparently not used, for "Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin/The Promised Land" and "Long Tongues: A Saxophone Opera." Holograph score for saxophone sextet (three altos, two tenors, and baritone), three pages long, with sections "Part I" and "Part II." A photocopy of this score has further annotations in Hemphill's hand in red ink. An additional manuscript page of "Part II" in pencil, not in Hemphill's hand, indicates expanded instrumentation, as in "Long Tongues."
- Homeboy Tootin' at the Dog Star, 1977-1995; cuid20488 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  Photocopy of holograph score from Foran Notebook, where it is titled "Eighth (Flute)." Included on the album Blue Boyé (1977).
- Hotend, 1977-1995; cuid20489 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  Photocopy of holograph score from Foran Notebook, where it is titled "Second." Composed for soprano and alto saxophones and included on the album Blue Boyé (1977).
- Hummer, 1968-1995; cuid20490 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  Photocopy of holograph score, two pages, for flute (See "Aggregated Parts" for original). Two other pieces, "Trills" and "Reflective," appear on the same manuscript pages.
- Images II, 1975-1995; cuid20491 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  Holograph score with the subtitle "Sketch II," composed for large ensemble, including winds, strings, saxophone sextet, and rhythm section, similar to the instrumentation used for "Long Tongues: A Saxophone Opera," which contains a movement entitled "Sketch II." Folder includes complete set of manuscript parts in black ink, not in Hemphill's hand.
- Impulse, 1975-1995; cuid20492 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  Holograph score and professionally copied parts for saxophone quartet (two alto, tenor, and baritone), in pencil and red ink. Folder includes a number of parts in various hands, as well as a set of professionally copied parts for a version orchestrated for two alto saxophones, tenor saxophone, two trumpets, trombone, French horn, violin, viola, and two unidentified instruments.
- Ink, 1980-1980; cuid20493 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  Holograph parts for saxophone quartet on mixed woodwinds (alto and tenor saxophone, bass clarinet, and baritone saxophone). Parts include names of World Saxophone Quartet members.
- It's a Mystery to Me, 1992-1992; cuid20494 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  Holograph transposing score for alto and baritone saxophones, guitar, cello, and drums. Folder includes a lead sheet in a different key and with some differences in melody from the score.
- Ji-Ji Tune, 1981-1995; cuid20495 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  Professionally copied parts for saxophone quartet (soprano, alto, tenor, and baritone). Composition is part of a suite entitled "Wind/Rhythms" written for World Saxophone Quartet's collaboration with Max Roach's M'Boom. The suite was apparently not performed at that concert. See "Wind/Rhythms" for full score.
- Kansas City Line, 1977-1995; cuid20496 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  Also appears under titles "K C Line," "Bop Scene: KC Line," or "Gates of Kansas City." Photocopy of holograph score from Foran Notebook for solo alto saxophone, bearing the title "Sixth Blues." Appears as sixth track on the album Blue Boyé (1977). Melody is a ten-bar blues form. Folder includes photocopy of holograph part with chord changes and melody in bass clef, as well as a holograph part with chord changes. There is also a holograph trumpet part and trumpet parts likely in Baikida Carroll's hand, photocopied from Trumpet Notebook and Bass Notebook. Appears as a movement in the large-scale works "Drunk on God" (for big band) and "Long Tongues: A Saxophone Opera."
- Lady S, 1980-1995; cuid20497 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  Holograph score in pencil and red ink for 12-piece big-band composition (five reeds, four brass, with three-piece rhythm section). Folder includes professionally copied parts on paper vellum.
- Lemon's Etched in Half-Mooned Blues, 1987-1995; cuid20498 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  Holograph score for saxophone sextet (soprano, two alto, two tenor, and baritone). Six-page score includes four printed pages of the poem "Collected Poem for Blind Lemon Jefferson" by K. Curtis Lyle, which was used for a recording in 1971. Score includes stage directions for musicians (possibly related to compositional process for "Long Tongues").
- Leora, 1986-1995; cuid20499 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  Holograph score for saxophone quartet (soprano, alto, tenor, and baritone). Second holograph score with instructions for arranging the quartet version for big band, including additional sections. Folder includes professionally copied parts for big band. A note from the copyist indicates that a full score of the big band arrangement was not made.
- Leora - Orchestral version, 1993-1995; cuid20500 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  Arrangement for orchestra by Scott Munson, commissioned by the Richmond Symphony. Folder includes computer-printed full score and parts, as well as a photocopy part for the saxophone soloist with chord changes.
- Let's Get It On, 1988-1995; cuid20501 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  Arrangement by Hemphill for saxophone quartet (soprano, alto, tenor, and baritone) of song by Marvin Gaye and Edward Townsend. Holograph score and photocopy of holograph with additions and corrections in Hemphill's hand.
- Lights, 1978-1995; cuid20502 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  Holograph score for soprano saxophone, flute, and bass. Fifteen-measure composition, with saxophone part apparently at concert pitch.
- Little Samba, 1968-1995; cuid20503 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  Holograph parts in black and red ink for saxophone quartet playing other woodwinds (flute, alto flute, tenor saxophone, and bass clarinet).
- Long Rhythm, 1977-1995; cuid20504 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  Photocopy of holograph part for cello (original is in "Aggregated Parts").
- Loopology, 1988-1995; cuid20505 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  Holograph score for saxophone quartet (soprano, alto, tenor, and baritone). Folder includes holograph part for baritone saxophone, though no other parts.
- Lush Life, 1986-1995; cuid20506 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  Arrangement of Billy Strayhorn composition by Hemphill for saxophone quartet (two alto, tenor, and baritone). Four-page holograph score, the latter two pages labeled "extra sheets" with solo sections. Folder includes notes by Hemphill, perhaps contemporaneous.
- M. Dewey-Davis System, 1968-1995; cuid20507 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Photocopy of holograph score from Musik Hug Notebook for saxophone and guitar.
- Mask Dance, 1987-1995; cuid20508 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  Holograph score for saxophone sextet (three alto, two tenor, and baritone) with instructions for drums. This piece was used in various stages of "Long Tongues" and possibly as part of "Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land."
- Maurice, 1968-1995; cuid20509 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Photocopy of holograph score for saxophone, guitar, trumpet, and cello/bass, notated in short score. Suite of five movements, only four of which are present: "II: Antecedent: Love/Understanding"; "III. Inquiry/Findings"; "IV. Tightenin'"; "V. Oracle." Pages numbered up to fifteen, though pages one, two, and ten are apparently missing. Folder includes photocopy of cello part for "Tightenin'" (original is in Aggregated Parts).
- Messin' With The Kid, 1988-1995; cuid20510 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Arrangement of Mel London composition by Hemphill for saxophone quartet (two alto, tenor, and baritone). Holograph concert score and professionally copied parts on paper and paper vellum.
- Middle of Here, 1968-1995; cuid20511 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Holograph part for cello of 26-measure composition. No other score or parts.
- Mingus Gold - Score, 1988-1995; cuid20512 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  Holograph score for string quartet (two violin, viola, cello) and photocopy of holograph with yellow sticky-note annotation. Adaptation/arrangement of three compositions by Charles Mingus: "Nostalgia in Times Square"; "Alice's Wonderland"; "Better Get Hit In Yo' Soul" (stylized by Hemphill as "Betta Gititin Yo Sole"). Folder also includes computer print-out of full score with annotations in red ink by Marty Ehrlich, as proofs for published edition.
- Mingus Gold - Parts, 1988-1995; cuid20513 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  Photocopies of complete set of professionally copied parts for string quartet, apparently for premiere performances by Kronos Quartet.
- Mirrors, 1971-1995; cuid20514 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Printouts of published full score for saxophone sextet (two soprano, alto, two tenor, and baritone) with guitar, as published by Subito Music. Folder includes various parts for small-group version for alto saxophone, trumpet, baritone saxophone, cello and guitar, most in holograph, but the trumpet part is a photocopy of a manuscript not in Hemphill's hand from Trumpet Notebook.
- Moat and the Bridge, The, 1988-1995; cuid20515 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  Holograph score (transposing) for saxophone sextet (three alto, two tenor, and baritone). Photocopies of professionally copied parts. Published in the Saxophone Sextet collection.
- Mosquito, 1968-1995; cuid20516 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  Two pages of holograph score. One page has composition in short score with indications for trumpet, guitar and bass. The other page is possibly an alto saxophone part, with chord symbols. Likely a piece for quintet of saxophone, trumpet, guitar, bass and drums.
- Mother of Pearl of Mother, 1968-1995; cuid20517 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Photocopy of fragmentary holograph score from Chiaroscuro Notebook. An eleven-measure melody for flute with part of a second line.
- Mr. Critical, 1988-1995; cuid20518 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Holograph score for saxophone sextet (two soprano, alto, two tenor, and baritone) with bass and drums. Dedication or homage to Ornette Coleman.
- My First Winter, 1981-1995; cuid20519 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Holograph score for saxophone quartet (three tenor and baritone). Page bears copyright symbol and date of 1981. Folder include professionally copied parts.
- New Prayers, 1980-1995; cuid20520 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Holograph parts for saxophone quartet on mixed woodwinds (flute, clarinet, and two soprano saxophones). The parts bear annotations likely by members of the World Saxophone Quartet, including a note on the clarinet part to transpose for alto clarinet.
- OK Rubberband, 1977-1995; cuid20521 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Photocopy of holograph score from Foran Notebook for soprano and alto saxophones and flute. In the notebook it bears the title "Third" and was the third track on the album Blue Boyé (1977), where it is titled "OK Rubberband."
- One Atmosphere, 1991-1995; cuid20522 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  Holograph score for piano and string quartet. Commissioned by Ursula Oppens and the Arditti String Quartet and premiered in February 1992. Folder includes photocopy of holograph score and photocopy of full score published by Subito.
- One for Eric, 1986-1995; cuid20523 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  Holograph score for Hemphill's arrangement of Jack DeJohnette composition for big band (five saxophones, five trumpets, four trombones, guitar, keyboard, bass, and drums). Folder includes professionally copied alto saxophone part, apparently from DeJohnette's small group version, with annotations by Hemphill likely in preparation for big-band arrangement.
- One for Stub, 1968-1995; cuid20524 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Holograph score for flute, alto and tenor saxophones, piano, bass, and drums. Ten-measure-long composition, dedicated to saxophonist John Stubblefield. Folder includes a manuscript copy of the score in an unknown hand, without measure numbers.
- One Two Three Four, 1976-1995; cuid20525 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Photocopy of holograph score from Foran Notebook of suite of four pieces for saxophone, trumpet, and percussion. The titles of the four pieces are stylized "#One"; "#Two"; "#Three" and "#Four." Folder includes photocopies of trumpet parts for the first three movements from Sightation Notebook. Of the four movements, only "Four" seems to have been performed as a free-standing piece. See "Four" for additional score and parts.
- One/Waltz/Time, 1985-1995; cuid20526 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Holograph score for saxophone quartet (two alto, tenor, and baritone) and photocopy of holograph score in Musik Hug Notebook of version for saxophone, two guitars, and bass. Folder includes holograph parts for cello, bass, guitar, tenor saxophone, and baritone saxophone.
- Open Air (For Tommy), 1978-1995; cuid20527 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Holograph score for twelve-piece big band, and holograph parts for version for saxophone quartet using mixed woodwinds (two alto/soprano saxophone, tenor saxophone / bass clarinet, alto clarinet / baritone saxophone). Folder includes holograph parts for alto saxophone and trumpet, perhaps for an arrangement for quartet.
- Opener, 1977-1995; cuid20528 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  Photograph of holograph score from Schirmer's Notebook for solo flute. Folder includes photocopy of untitled melody for flute from preceding pages in notebook.
- Opening (Hymn), 1990-1995; cuid20529 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  Photocopies of professionally copied parts for saxophone sextet (two soprano, alto, two tenor, and baritone). This piece was composed for "Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land" and performed separately in concert by the Julius Hemphill Sextet. See "Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin" for holograph score and parts.
- Orientation of Sweet Willie Rollbar, The, 1972-1975; cuid20530 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  Photocopy of holograph score for flute, trumpet, and drums, from Kawaida Notebook, with title "Rollbar," beginning at "Sec. VI." Likely related to Hemphill's score for the film "The Orientation of Sweet Willie Rollbar" (1972).
- Otis' Groove, 1988-1995; cuid20531 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  Professionally copied parts for saxophone sextet (three alto, two tenor, and baritone). This piece was also incorporated into large-scale works. See "Last Supper at Uncle Tom's Cabin / The Promised Land" and "Long Tongues: A Saxophone Opera" for score and parts.